The Lives of the Prophets; Part 2
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
Before I go to the next section of the story of Musa(موسى);
Let's look at the story of Musa(موسى) up to this point.
Until now, up to this point, Musa(موسى) is not a prophet yet; He's not the messenger.
So, why is Allahسُبحانه وتعالى telling us all of this history record of the life of Musa(موسى) before Risaalah(رسالة), before the message-hood or prophet-hood?
You know, it's very important for us to know this background of Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى).
Because Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is putting Musa(موسى) through experiences that he will need in his mission, as a messenger.
First of all, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى raised up Musa(موسى) in the palace of Firaun(فرعون).
So that Musa(موسى) can be an insider; He sees how the government functions from the inside.
So he has expertise; He knows what's happening.
Just like, what happened with Yusuf(يوسُف)?
Where was he raised?
He was raised in the house of the prime minister or the treasure.
So he has knowledge of how the governments functions and works.
Also, Musa(موسى) has first-hand knowledge of the corruption of Firaun(فرعون), because he has seen it with his own eyes.
And look at the travelling of Musa(موسى).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى made Musa(موسى) travel out of Egypt.
And we know that Al-Imaam-Al-Shaafi(امام الشافى) says;
تَغَرَّب عَنِ الأَوطانِ في طَلَبِ العُلا وَسافِر فَفي الأَسفارِ خَمسُ فَوائِدِ
تَفَرُّجُ هَمٍّ وَاِكتِسابُ مَعيشَةٍ وَعِلمٌ وَآدابٌ وَصُحبَةُ ماجِدِ
Imaam-Al-Shaafi(امام الشافى) says; Leave your country in search of exaltation
and travel because there are five benefits in traveling;
To relief your despair,
to seek a livelihood,
to seek knowledge,
to seek manners and new behaviors,
and finally he said; to be accompanying somebody who is righteous.
These are benefits that you could get through traveling.
So, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى made Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى) travel in the land so that, he can learn.
Number three;
What type of job did Musa(موسى) serve, when he was working with this man?
راعي الغنم
A shepherd of goat or sheep.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
ما من نبي الا ورعى الغنم
Every prophet has been a shepherd of sheep.
Why specifically sheep and why specifically a shepherd?
Being a shepherd is being responsible.
And being a shepherd of sheep. ?
Sheep are the weakest of the livestock that we have.
It is weaker than cows and it's weaker than camels.
And that weakness makes the shepherd very alert.
He has to have his eyes always open to take care and guard these sheep from a wolf;
to take care of them of being lost.
Because the sheep cannot survive on its own but the camel can.
So, the shepherd learns how to be very alert.
Because the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) are going to be protecting a whole nation; a whole nation of weak people.
Because;
خُلِقَ الْإِنْسَانُ ضَعِيفًا۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; the human being is weak.
So, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى makes them go through this training; of being shepherds.
So that, they learn; how to be responsible.
Because it's the responsibility of the shepherd to take care of the flock.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى was preparing Musa(موسى) for what?
Allah was preparing him for the most difficult job of all.
The most difficult job of all is the job of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء).
That's the most difficult work; It is the work of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
And the particular work of Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى) was going to be one of the most challenging work that any Nabi(نَبِي) has faced.
Because, who is Musa(موسى) going to be dealing with?
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is sending him to Firaun(فرعون).
Allah is sending him to the man; who claimed to be God.
أَنَا۠ رَبُّكُمُ ٱلْأَعْلَى۝
وَمَا عَلِمْتُ لَكُم مِّنْ إِلَٰهٍ غَيْرِي
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is sending Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى) to face the oldest monarchy living on the face of the earth and that is the family of Firaun(فرعون).
This family who believed that divine blood is running through their veins.
They believe that they are the seeds of God; that they are the children of God.
This family that rule over an empire of the rich Nile River.
They have been ruling for centuries and centuries and nobody dares to stand against them.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is going to send one man against this strong, powerful family headed by Firaun(فرعون).
A superpower or an empire or civilization of his time.
That's on one hand.
On the other hand; Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is sending Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى) to deal with Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل);
A nation that has some remnants of the religion of Allah.
But it has been mixed with so much culture and tradition, that it has a different face.
And they have been living under oppression for a very long time.
And that oppression has eroded the dignity that they have.
And it has caused their personalities to be humiliated.
And that is what happens to people when they live under oppression for a long time.
And we found that in the story of Musa(موسى) and the two men who are fighting;
one of them was from children of Israel and one of them was from the Egyptians.
When Musa(موسى) came to interfere, what did the Bani Israeli(بني أسرائيلى) say?
He said; You want to kill me like you have killed somebody the day before.
So, he betrayed Musa(موسى), who helped him the day before.
So, you find that the people who live under oppression for a very long time; they become very selfish.
Because the government makes sure that they are divided.
Because if they're united; the government will not survive.
So, they divide the people.
They plant the seeds of division among them.
So, then you have people who are living in their own islands.
They are thinking individualistically in a selfish way.
These are the kind of people that Musa(موسى) is going to deal with.
A kind of people who lost dignity.
اذْهَبْ أَنتَ وَرَبُّكَ فَقَاتِلَا
Go and fight with your Lord, we're going to sit right here.
So, this was the mission; the difficult mission, that Syedina Musa(عليه الصلوة والسلام) was going to be faced with.
But until now, Musa(موسى) has no idea, what Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is hiding for him in the future?
Musa(موسى) has been away from his mother and his family and his country for 10 years.
He feels homesick; He misses his family.
He wants to go back and visit his mother; He wants to visit his family.
So, he decided that he's going to go to Egypt; Secretly, he will sneak in, without the government knowing
and go and meet with his family and relatives.
So, he took with him his wife and he started traveling towards Egypt.
Musa(موسى) got lost; He lost the directions.
It was a very cold and dark night.
And Musa(موسى) is traveling in this cold and dark night.
He lost direction; There is no light; It was completely dark and it was very cold.
And Musa(موسى) is with his wife; alone, in this very difficult environment; its desert.
That area which is between Ash-Sham(ألشَّام)  and Egypt, is desert.
Musa(موسى) saw; what appeared to be fire far away.
And it seems from the Ayaat(آيات); that only Musa(موسى) was able to see it but his wife didn't see it.
إِنِّي آنَسْتُ نَارًا
I have seen light.
It seems that this light; because it was a special light only Musa(موسى) was seeing it; his wife couldn't recognize it.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَلَمَّا قَضَىٰ مُوسَى الْأَجَلَ وَسَارَ بِأَهْلِهِ آنَسَ مِن جَانِبِ الطُّورِ نَارًا۝
And, he was traveling with his family.
He saw a fire in the direction of At-Toor(الطور).
He told his wife; wait here, I will go and either try to find directions.
Because, that fire must be burned by some people; there must be some people around it.
So, they'll give me directions; I need guidance.
Musa(موسى) needs guidance.
He says;
لَعَلِّيْ أَجِدُ عَلَى النَّارِ هُدًى۝
That I will find guidance next to the fire.
What guidance is he talking about?
Directions to Egypt.
لَّعَلِّیْۤ اٰتِیْكُمْ مِّنْهَا بِقَبَسٍ اَوْ اَجِدُ عَلَى النَّارِ هُدًى۝
So that I could either bring you some light because we need light; we are in complete darkness
or I will find the guidance.
لَّعَلِّیْۤ اٰتِیْكُمْ مِّنْهَا بِقَبَسٍ اَوْ اَجِدُ عَلَى النَّارِ هُدًى۝
So, Musa(موسى) walked to that direction.
Musa(موسى) doesn't know, what he's going to face in front of him?
He walks there and Allahسُبحانه وتعالى tells us about one of the most amazing conversations that happened in the history of the universe.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَلَمَّآ أَتَىٰهَا نُودِىَ مِن شَٰطِئِ ٱلْوَادِ ٱلْأَيْمَنِ فِى ٱلْبُقْعَةِ ٱلْمُبَٰرَكَةِ مِنَ ٱلشَّجَرَةِ
أَن يَٰمُوسَىٰٓ إِنِّىٓ أَنَا ٱللَّهُ رَبُّ ٱلْعَٰلَمِينَ۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
So when he reached the fire.
He was called from the right side of the valley, in the blessed place from the tree.
Oh Musa(موسى)! Verily, I am Allah; the Lord of Al-Alameen(العالمين).
And then, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told Musa(موسى);
اِنِّیْۤ اَنَا رَبُّكَ فَاخْلَعْ نَعْلَیْكَۚ-
اِنَّكَ بِالْوَادِ الْمُقَدَّسِ طُوًى۝
Oh Musa(موسى)! Take off your shoes because you are in the Sacred Valley.
You have to come into this meeting with preparation; take off your shoes.
Just like, we enter into Salah(صلاة) with Wudhu(وضو).
So he went in, to that sacred valley; in At-Toor(الطور).
And then he saw this tree; green tree.
There was fire burning in it but the tree is becoming more green and green.
And that fire was not fire but it was light.
And then he watched and he saw that light was extending up to the Samawat(سماوات).
And then Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told him;
اِنَّنِیْۤ اَنَا اللّٰهُ لَاۤ اِلٰهَ اِلَّاۤ اَنَا
I am Allah, there's no God but Me.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى spoke to Musa(موسى) in those special moments.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى);
اِنَّنِیْۤ اَنَا اللّٰهُ لَاۤ اِلٰهَ اِلَّاۤ اَنَا فَاعْبُدْنِیْۙ-وَ اَقِمِ الصَّلٰوةَ لِذِكْرِیْ۝
There's no god but Me; So, worship me and establish prayer for My remembrance.
And then Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told him;
إِنَّ السَّاعَةَ آتِيَةٌ أَكَادُ أُخْفِيهَا لِتُجْزَى كُلُّ نَفْسٍ بِمَا تَسْعَى۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told Musa(موسى) about the hour; the day of Judgment; Al-Akhira(الآخرة).
Now let's go back a little bit.
Musa(موسى), what did he want from this fire?
He wanted two things.
He wanted light; to light up the small area which he and his wife and his sheep are sitting in
but he came back with light for humanity.
Musa(موسى) went to that fire because he wants guidance,
so that someone will tell him the direction to Egypt but he came back for guidance for mankind.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told him;
إِنَّنِىٓ أَنَا ٱللَّهُ لَآ إِلَٰهَ إِلَّآ أَنَا۠ فَٱعْبُدْنِى
I am Allah so worship Me;
Tawheed(تؤحيد); Number one;
Oneness of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى and what was the next order after Tawheed(تؤحيد)?
أَقِمِ ٱلصَّلَوٰةَ لِذِكْرِىٓ۝
Established prayer for my remembrance.
Salah(صلاة) was prescribed on Musa(موسى) in a direct conversation between him and Allah.
And how was Salah(صلاة) prescribed on Muhammadﷺ.?
It was prescribed on him in the trip of Al-Mairaj(المعراج) without anyone in between.
That is the importance of Salah(صلاة).
And then Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told him, what He has told every prophet?
And that is the people need to believe in the Akhira(آخرة); in the afterlife.
السَّاعَةَ آتِيَةٌ
The hour will come.
أَكَادُ أُخْفِيهَا
I am hiding it; It's so close; If it is there, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى just hiding it away from the people.
In this wonderful conversation between the creator and the servant; Musa عليه السلام.
Musa(موسى) is holding his stick.
He's holding his stick which he has lived with for a very long time. He knows his stick very well.
Musa(موسى) knows his stick very well.
So, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى asks him about his stick.
وَمَا تِلْكَ بِيَمِينِكَ يَا مُوسَى۝
What is that in your hands, Oh Musa(موسى)?
What is in your right hand?
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى wants him to say; what he knows about his stick.
Because Allah wants to show him, what he doesn't know.
So, Musa(موسى) told Allahسُبحانه وتعالى
according to his knowledge, what he knows about this stick which he has owned for a very long time.
He said;
قَالَ هِيَ عَصَايَ أَتَوَكَّأُ عَلَيْهَا وَأَهُشُّ بِهَا عَلَى غَنَمِي وَلِيَ فِيهَا مَآرِبُ أُخْرَى۝
He said; This is my stick, where on I lean and where with I beat down branches for my sheep and where in I find other uses.
I use it to lean on when I need to climb
and I use it to beat down branches and leaves to feed my sheep.
And I also use it for other things.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told Musa(موسى);
أَلْقِهَا يَا مُوسَى۝
Throw it.
So Musa(موسى) threw away his stick and what happened?
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَأَنْ أَلْقِ عَصَاكَ ۖ
فَلَمَّا رَءَاهَا تَهْتَزُّ كَأَنَّهَا جَآنٌّ وَلَّىٰ مُدْبِرًا وَلَمْ يُعَقِّبْ ۚ
So, he threw his stick from his hand and it started to shake.
The stick is dead but Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is the One Who created life and death.
So that stick that is dead; Allahسُبحانه وتعالى put in it, a soul of a snake.
For Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, it is exactly as creating anything else.
For Allahسُبحانه وتعالى; it is Kun-Fayakun(كُنْ فَيَكُونُ).
But this is unusual for Musa(موسى) who knows his stick for a very long time.
So when Musa(موسى);
رَءَاهَا تَهْتَزُّ كَأَنَّهَا جَآنٌّ
It started shaking like a huge serpent.
Musa(موسى); what was his first reaction?
It was a reaction of a human being.
فَوَلَّىٰ مُدْبِرًا وَلَمْ يُعَقِّبْ ۚ
He ran away and he did not look back; He ran away;
He didn't even look back.
Because this is a stick which he knew for a very long time and now suddenly, it's a huge Snake.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is training Musa(موسى).
This natural human fear has to get out of his heart.
This is natural; It is a natural human trait to have fear in your heart.
But Musa(موسى) is going to be dealing with situations and he has to have a strong heart.
So Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is preparing him for that.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told Musa(موسى);
يَا مُوسَىٰ أَقْبِلْ وَلَا تَخَفْ ۖ إِنَّكَ مِنَ الْآمِنِينَ۝
Oh Musa(موسى)! come here and do not have any fear because you are going to be safe and secure.
So Musa(موسى) came back.
And then Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told him;
وَاضْمُمْ يَدَكَ إِلَىٰ جَنَاحِكَ
Put your right hand under your arm.
Musa(موسى) was dark skinned, as we said.
He pulled out his hand it was white and shining like the moon.
Allah told them to put his hand back; He put his hand back; it returned to it's natural colour.
Two signs;
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
لنريك من اياتنا الكبرى۝
That we may show you, some of our greater signs.
These are two, out of nine signs; Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given Musa(موسى) and we'll talk about the other signs later.
Now, hold your breath for the next thing.
This is a short conversation between Allah and Musa(موسى).
Musa(موسى) is just confronted with the responsibility.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is handing down Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى); the responsibility of Prophet-hood.
But what was the first command that Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given Musa(موسى)?
اِذْهَبْ اِلٰى فِرْعَوْنَ
Go to Firaun(فرعون), immediately.
Musa(موسى) just received the message right now.
And in this conversation between him Allah;
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is already handing him; the challenging mission of going and facing Firaun(فرعون).
اِذْهَبْ اِلٰى فِرْعَوْنَ اِنَّهٗ طَغٰى۝
Go to Firaun(فرعون) because he has transgressed all bounds.
This is a very, very heavy order.
قَوْلًا ثَقِيلً
This is heavy.
Musa(موسى) ran out of Egypt for 10 years because of fear of Firaun(فرعون).
He wants to visit his family and his mother and his relatives and his home country.
He's not going there because of the fear of Firaun(فرعون).
And now, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is telling him not to go into Egypt; to go to Firaun(فرعون) and tell him to follow you.
But Musa عليه السلام; Allahسُبحانه وتعالى chose him because of his strength and his Eeman(ايمان).
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى
يَجْتَبِي
He chooses out of his creation, the best for this mission of Prophet-hood.
So Musa(موسى) did not reject the command of Allah.
But he asked Allah for help.
Because this is not an easy thing to do.
So, he told Allahسُبحانه وتعالى;
قَالَ رَبِّ اشْرَحْ لِي صَدْرِي۝
Notice and look at this wonderful Dua(دُعَا) of Musa(موسى), what he's asking from Allah?
Number one;
قَالَ رَبِّ اشْرَحْ لِي صَدْرِي۝
Oh Allah! Open up; my heart and my chest.
Open for me my chest; Grant me self confidence and contentment and boldness.
This mission of facing Firaun(فرعون), needs to have a very strong heart.
So, open for me my heart, give me strength, give me confidence.
وَيَسِّرْ لِي أَمْرِي۝
And make my mission easy.
Because Allahسُبحانه وتعالى can make the difficult easy.
وَاحْلُلْ عُقْدَةً مِّن لِّسَانِي۝
And make loose the knot; the defect from my tongue.
Musa(موسى) had a problem with speech.
We do not know what exactly there's that story of the charcoal and all that but there's no evidence for it.
Anyway, we know from the Nas(نص) of Qur'an; from the text of Qur'an that Musa(موسى) had the problem with the way, he used to speak.
Either, it was difficulty in pronouncing letters
or it was difficulty in expressing himself
or difficultly in he was tattering, AllahuAalam(اللَّهُ أَعْلَمُ).
But he had certain defect in the way he used to speak.
So, he asked Allahسُبحانه وتعالى;
وَاحْلُلْ عُقْدَةً مِّن لِّسَانِي۝
And release one of the knots from my tongue.
He didn't ask Allah to make him the most fluent;
He asked Allahسُبحانه وتعالى to release that knot as much as he would need.
Ayeshaرضى الله عنه was going to Hajj(حَجْ); And she heard some men talking outside.
And one of them is asking; he's giving them a quiz.
He said;
من امن الناس على أخى؟
Who did the greatest favor on his brother?
He's asking these men, who did the biggest favor to his brother?
Ayesha(عائشه) from inside her Hawdij(هودج) from over the camel; She responded and said;
Musa(موسى); he is the one who did the biggest favour on his brother Haroon(هارون).
Because the biggest favour is that Musa(موسى) asked Allah to make Haroon(هارون) a prophet.
What bigger favour could you do for your brother?
He asked Allah; Oh Allah! make my brother a prophet.
No brother has done his brother a favour like Musa(موسى) has done; Haroon(هارون).
وَاجْعَل لِّي وَزِيرًا مِّنْ أَهْلِي۝
And appoint for me a helper from my family.
هَارُونَ أَخِى۝
Haroon(هارون); My brother.
And then notice here the rules of brotherhood in Islam are in the following Ayaat(آيات).
Why does he want help from his brother Haroon(هارون)?
اشْدُدْ بِهِ أَزْرِي۝
To increase my strength with him.
Your brother and you are stronger together.
That's one purpose of brotherhood in Islam.
You become stronger when you have a brother.
When you're alone, you're not as strong as when you have a brother.
And that's why Rasool Allah ﷺ has always told us to be with the Jama'ah(جماعة).
Don't think that you can survive alone in the wilderness outside.
Outside; is a jungle; It's a jungle and you need to be with the Muslims because you are like sheep.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
إنما يأكل الذئب الغنم القاصية
The wolf eats from the stray sheep.
The wolf will not attack the pack; the flock.
The wolf will attack the sheep which is alone.
اشْدُدْ بِهِ أَزْرِي۝
That's number one.
And then; and let him share my task.
So he will help me in my tasks.
Brotherhood in Islam is not for worldly benefit or gain.
Brotherhood in Islam is for;
كَىْ نُسَبِّحَكَ كَثِيرًا۝
وَنَذْكُرَكَ كَثِيرًا۝
إِنَّكَ كُنتَ بِنَا بَصِيرًا۝
That we may glorify You much, and remember You much, verily You are of us ever a well-seer.
We can worship You together; That's why I want to have a brother.
So that, we can both worship Allahسُبحانه وتعالى and make Tasbeeh(تسبيه) and Dhikr(ذكر) for Allah.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said;
قَالَ قَدْ أُوتِيتَ سُؤْلَكَ يَا مُوسَىٰ۝
Allah said; You are granted your request, Oh Musa(موسى)!.
Allah granted him his request.
Now, there are few other points which Musa(موسى) wants to ask Allahسُبحانه وتعالى about.
Musa(موسى) has left Egypt because of the murder case that happened.
There was a warrant against Musa(موسى).
So, he wants to ask about Allahسُبحانه وتعالى about this.
He says;
قَالَ رَبِّ إِنِّى قَتَلْتُ مِنْهُمْ نَفْسًا فَأَخَافُ أَن يَقْتُلُونِ۝
He said; My Lord! I have killed a man among them and I fear that they may kill me.
وَأَخِى هَٰرُونُ هُوَ أَفْصَحُ مِنِّى لِسَانًا فَأَرْسِلْهُ مَعِىَ رِدْءًا يُصَدِّقُنِىٓ ۖ
إِنِّىٓ أَخَافُ أَن يُكَذِّبُونِ۝
قَالَ سَنَشُدُّ عَضُدَكَ بِأَخِيكَ وَنَجْعَلُ لَكُمَا سُلْطَٰنًا فَلَا يَصِلُونَ إِلَيْكُمَا ۚ
بِـَٔايَٰتِنَآ أَنتُمَا وَمَنِ ٱتَّبَعَكُمَا ٱلْغَٰلِبُونَ۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; he said, my Lord! I have killed a man among them and I fear that they will kill me.
And my brother; Haroon(هارون), he is more eloquent in speech than me; He's better in speaking.
So, send him with me as a helper to confirm me.
Verily, I fear that they will belie me.
Allah said; We will strengthen your arm through your brother and give you both power.
So, they shall not be able to harm you with our Ayaat(آيات).
You two as well as those who follow you will be victorious.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told Musa(موسى); now to go to Firaun(فرعون).
Go with your brother to Firaun(فرعون) and Allahسُبحانه وتعالى gave him advice.
اذْهَبَا إِلَى فِرْعَوْنَ إِنَّهُ طَغَى۝
فَقُولَا لَهُ قَوْلًا لَيِّنًا لَعَلَّهُ يَتَذَكَّرُ أَوْ يَخْشَى۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; Go both of you to Pharaoh, verily he has transgressed.
And what is the advice?
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى said; and speak to him mildly.
قَوْلًا لَيِّنًا
Layyin(لَيِّن) means, soft and mild.
What is the wisdom behind that?
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
لَعَلَّهُ يَتَذَكَّرُ أَوْ يَخْشَى۝
Perhaps, he may accept admonition or fear Allah.
If you speak to someone mildly and softly, there is a possibility that, he will fear Allah and he would remember.
If you speak to them roughly, most likely they won't.
So, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is telling Musa(موسى) the manners of Da'wah(دعوة).
It has to be done in a soft manner; It has to be done in a mild way; That is how it should be done.
I want to mention one thing in regards to Da'wah(دعوة) here.
Sometimes we think that part of being mild in Da'wah(دعوة) is to not threaten the other side or make them worry.
Sometimes in our Da'wah(دعوة); we tell the people about Islam but we shy away from mentioning to them the consequences of not believing.
We sometimes hold back telling the people, if you don't believe, this is what will happen to you; You will be in hellfire.
We think that, that is too harsh.
Is that true or not?
We find here the answer in the Ayaat(آيات).
The Ayah(آية) that says talk to Firaun(فرعون) in a mild fashion is Ayah(آية) forty four in Surah-Taha(سورة طه).
Ayah(آية) forty eight in Surah-Taha(سورة طه); Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is telling that Musa(موسى) is saying to Firaun(فرعون);
إِنَّا قَدْ أُوحِىَ إِلَيْنَآ أَنَّ ٱلْعَذَابَ عَلَىٰ مَن كَذَّبَ وَتَوَلَّىٰ۝
Musa(موسى) is telling Firaun(فرعون); Truly it has been revealed to us that torment will be for him, who denies and turns away from Allah.
So Musa(موسى) is telling Firaun(فرعون); I have received revelation that if you don't believe in Allah, you will be punished in hellfire.
Therefore, Allahسُبحانه وتعالى tells us that we should be mild and soft in our Da'wah(دعوة).
But this is not part of it.
Why?
Because this is part of the honesty of conveying the message.
The Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) of Allah have been given an Amanah(امانة); trust.
And they have to be honest.
They cannot hold back information from people.
They have to tell them the truth.
بَشِيرًا وَنَذِيرًا
To give them the glad tidings and to give them the warning.
If you believe; you would receive Jannah(جنة); If you don't believe; you would receive Hellfire.
Anyway, Musa(موسى) and Haroon(هارون), they said;
قَالَا رَبَّنَاۤ إِنَّنَا نَخَافُ أَن یَفۡرُطَ عَلَیۡنَاۤ أَوۡ أَن یَطۡغَىٰ۝
Oh Allah! We fear that they should hasten to punish us or lest, they should transgress.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى told them; fear not, verily, I am with you both hearing and seeing.
So Musa(موسى) and Haroon(هارون); they had different conversations with Firaun(فرعون)
and Allahسُبحانه وتعالى mentions that in many parts of Qur'an.
We'll talk about this one here.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى in many Ayaat(آيات) mentions this.
This one is in Surat(سورت) Ash-Shu'ara(الشعراء).
When Musa(موسى) went to Firaun(فرعون) and asked him to believe in Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
Firaun(فرعون) immediately started reminding Musa(موسى) with his previous crime.
And he also started reminding Musa(موسى) with his favours on him.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
قَالَ أَلَمْ نُرَبِّكَ فِينَا وَلِيدًا وَلَبِثْتَ فِينَا مِنْ عُمُرِكَ سِنِينَ۝
Pharaoh said to Musa(موسى); Did we not bring you up among us as a child?
And we did dwell many years and you did dwell many years of your life with us.
I'm the one who raised you up; I'm the one who fed you; I'm the one who took care of you.
And this is what you end up doing to me.
And the other thing he said;
وَفَعَلْتَ فَعْلَتَكَ ٱلَّتِى فَعَلْتَ وَأَنتَ مِنَ ٱلْكَٰفِرِينَ۝
And you did your deed, which you did.
He's talking about what?
The crime of killing.
And you were one of the ungrates; you were ungrateful.
We took care of you and then you ended up, killing one of our people.
The response of Musa(موسى) was amazing.
Very interesting response.
Firaun(فرعون) has done Musa(موسى) a favour right; A big favour.
He raised him up for years in his palace as an adopted son and took care of him for all of his life.
How could you now come and talk to me this way?
It's a big favor.
But look at the response of Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى).
He said;
وَتِلْكَ نِعْمَةٌ تَمُنُّهَا عَلَىَّ أَنْ عَبَّدتَّ بَنِىٓ إِسْرَٰٓءِيلَ۝
Is this a favor you are telling me about, when you have enslave the children of Israel(اسرائيل)?
What was the reason, Musa(موسى) was raised up in the house of Firaun(فرعون)?
It is because of the oppression of Firaun(فرعون) to Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
If it wasn't for that oppression, Musa(موسى) would have been raised by his own parents; He did not need Firaun(فرعون).
He did not need Firaun(فرعون).
The only reason; why Musa(موسى) was raised by Firaun(فرعون) is because of the oppression of Firaun(فرعون) against Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
And because of that oppression, he ended up raising up Musa(موسى).
Otherwise Musa(موسى) would have been in his house, his mother would not put him in the river.
His mother put him in a river because of the fear of Firaun(فرعون).
If Firaun(فرعون) was not oppressive and Zalim(ظالم); he would have been raised in his own house.
So, Musa(موسى) is telling him; what favor are you talking about? That's not the favor.
That is because of your oppression against Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل).
So don't tell me that, that's a favor.
And then he talked about the crime.
He Musa عليه السلام said;
قَالَ فَعَلْتُهَا إِذًا وَأَنَا مِنَ الضَّالِّينَ۝
I did it in a time of ignorance; I was ignorant at the time.
فَفَرَرْتُ مِنكُمْ لَمَّا خِفْتُكُمْ فَوَهَبَ لِى رَبِّى حُكْمًا وَجَعَلَنِى مِنَ ٱلْمُرْسَلِينَ۝
And then I ran away from you and then Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given me the message.
So don't hold me accountable for something that I did then.
Because at that time I was ignorant.
But now, I have the message from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
وَجَعَلَنِى مِنَ ٱلْمُرْسَلِينَ۝
He made me of the messengers.
قَالَ فِرْعَوْنُ وَمَا رَبُّ ٱلْعَٰلَمِينَ۝
Firaun(فرعون) said; who is; who is the God of the world; Who is He?
Who are you talking about; Who's your Lord?
Musa(موسى) said;
قَالَ رَبُّ ٱلسَّمَٰوَٰتِ وَٱلْأَرْضِ وَمَا بَيْنَهُمَآ ۖ إِن كُنتُم مُّوقِنِينَ۝
He said; The Lord of the Heavens and the Earth and all that is in between them.
If you seek to be convinced with certainty.
Musa(موسى) is talking serious.
He's saying; Allah is the Lord of the Heavens and the Earth.
Firaun(فرعون) wants to turn it into joke and entertainment.
So, he started making fun of Musa(موسى).
قَالَ لِمَنْ حَوْلَهُۥٓ أَلَا تَسْتَمِعُونَ۝
So, he started to make fool out of Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى); mocking at Syedina Musaعليه السلام .
Musa(موسى) did not respond to that; he was not sidetracked.
Musa(موسى) continued and said;
قَالَ رَبُّكُمْ وَرَبُّ آبَائِكُمُ الْأَوَّلِينَ۝
He is your Lord and the Lord of your forefathers before you.
Now, Firaun(فرعون) got angry.
قَالَ إِنَّ رَسُولَكُمُ ٱلَّذِىٓ أُرْسِلَ إِلَيْكُمْ لَمَجْنُونٌ۝
He said; the messenger who is sent to you is crazy.
Now, he started getting serious and angry and he is accusing Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى) of insanity.
Musa(موسى) did not respond to that either and he continued.
Look at the Daiyah(داعيه);
قَالَ رَبُّ ٱلْمَشْرِقِ وَٱلْمَغْرِبِ وَمَا بَيْنَهُمَآ ۖ إِن كُنتُمْ تَعْقِلُونَ۝
He is the Lord of the East and the West and everything in between, if you have any understanding.
And this is an important lesson of Da'wah(دعوة); Don't protect your own self in Da'wah(دعوة).
We would be talking with somebody about Da'wah(دعوة); giving them the message;
they will attack us; we start defending our ownselves.
And we'll get into the conversation and the debate of defending our ownselves.
Firaun(فرعون) starts accusing him; Musa(موسى) is continuing with the signs of Allah.
And now, Firaon(فرعون) goes from the next step; He started with mockery and then accusing and then now, threatening.
قَالَ لَئِنِ ٱتَّخَذْتَ إِلَٰهًا غَيْرِى لَأَجْعَلَنَّكَ مِنَ ٱلْمَسْجُونِينَ۝
If you take any other God beside me, I will throw you in jail.
Musa(موسى) said;
قَالَ أَوَلَوْ جِئْتُكَ بِشَىْءٍۢ مُّبِينٍۢ۝
What, if I bring you with clear signs from Allah.
Firaun(فرعون) told him; show me what you have.
Musa(موسى) threw his stick.
فَإِذَا هِىَ ثُعْبَانٌ مُّبِينٌ۝
It turned into a snake.
وَنَزَعَ يَدَهُۥ فَإِذَا هِىَ بَيْضَآءُ لِلنَّٰظِرِينَ۝
And he took out his hand from under his arm and it was white for all of them around him.
Now, Firaun(فرعون) said that Musa(موسى) is a magician.
قَالَ لِلْمَلَإِ حَوْلَهُۥٓ إِنَّ هَٰذَا لَسَٰحِرٌ عَلِيمٌ۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى has given Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى) the Ayaat(آيات).
Firaun(فرعون) refuse to follow the signs, which he has seen with his own eyes and accused Musa of being a sorcerer; a magician.
Firaun(فرعون) announced that, he will gather all of the magicians of Egypt and bring them to challenge Syedina Musaعليه السلام.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَلَقَدْ أَرَيْنَٰهُ ءَايَٰتِنَا كُلَّهَا فَكَذَّبَ وَأَبَىٰ۝
We showed Firaun(فرعون) all of our signs; Nevertheless, he still rejected and refused.
قَالَ أَجِئْتَنَا لِتُخْرِجَنَا مِنْ أَرْضِنَا بِسِحْرِكَ يَٰمُوسَىٰ۝
Oh Musa(موسى)! do you want to drive us out of our land with your magic.
So, he accused Musa(موسى) of trying to take over the government and drive them out of the land.
This is the thing he accused Musa(موسى) of doing.
لِتُخْرِجَنَا مِنْ أَرْضِنَا
You want to drive us out of our land, take over the government and kick us out.
He said; you want to do that with your magic.
We have stronger magic than yours.
فَلَنَأْتِيَنَّكَ بِسِحْرٍۢ مِّثْلِهِۦ فَٱجْعَلْ بَيْنَنَا وَبَيْنَكَ مَوْعِدًا لَّا نُخْلِفُهُۥ نَحْنُ وَلَآ أَنتَ مَكَانًا سُوًى۝
We going to bring you with magic similar to it and better.
فَٱجْعَلْ بَيْنَنَا وَبَيْنَكَ مَوْعِدًا لَّا نُخْلِفُهُۥ نَحْنُ وَلَآ أَنتَ مَكَانًا سُوًى۝
So, let's have an appointed time.
Musa(موسى) chose the day of Al-Zeenah(الزينه).
This is the Festival of the people of Egypt.
On that day, all of the people would gather together and they would have a big celebration.
Musa(موسى) chose that day because he wants everybody to be there and he wants everyone to see the signs of Allah.
قَالَ مَوْعِدُكُمْ يَوْمُ ٱلزِّينَةِ وَأَن يُحْشَرَ ٱلنَّاسُ ضُحًى۝
The appointed time is your festival day and we'll meet in the early morning.
When all of the people come together, then we're gonna start our competition.
فَتَوَلَّىٰ فِرْعَوْنُ فَجَمَعَ كَيْدَهُۥ ثُمَّ أَتَىٰ۝
Firaun(فرعون) left and he brought together all of his strength and power.
قَالَ لَهُم مُّوسَىٰ وَيْلَكُمْ لَا تَفْتَرُواْ عَلَى ٱللَّهِ كَذِبًا فَيُسْحِتَكُم بِعَذَابٍۢ ۖ
Musa(موسى); when he saw all of the magicians present,
it says in another Ayah(آية) that Firaun(فرعون) has sent to all of the towns of Egypt to gather all of the magicians.
He has sent his orders to bring all of the magicians from Egypt.
What was the role of the magicians in Egypt?
First of all, we need to realize that Allahسُبحانه وتعالى, when He sends a prophet;
He provides the Nabi(نَبِي) with miracles that challenge the people in their field of expertise.
So the people of Egypt; the most high ranking science that they had; and their field of expertise was; the field of magic.
They were very powerful in that field and maybe the world, until today has never seen such powerful magic like; what existed in Egypt.
They were the top in magic.
Firaun(فرعون) used to use the magicians to control and dominate the minds of the society.
He would use them to influence and control the minds of people.
So these were working with Firaun(فرعون).
And that's why they say in another Ayah(آية).
وَمَآ أَكْرَهْتَنَا عَلَيْهِ مِنَ ٱلسِّحْرِ ۗ
They were forced to learn this.
And Firaun(فرعون) would have schools, where they would teach them the magic.
And then he would use it to control the minds of people; through magic.
And to give the people the impression, that Firaun(فرعون) is God.
And these magicians would commit these strange acts of magic
and they will do it in the name of Firaun(فرعون) and that is how, they control the lives of people in Egypt.
But Firaun(فرعون) was very terrified from this single man Syedina Musaعليه السلام.
So, he didn't bring one magician or two.
He brought the best magicians that Egypt could offer.
And there are different narrations; We don't know how much for sure.
Ibn-e-Ashaab(ابن اسحاب) goes as far as saying; 15,000
but Ibn Abbas(إبن عباس) says; 70.
So let's go with the least and that is the narration of Ibn Abbas(إبن عباس) seventy magicians.
These 70 magicians were standing in front of Musa(موسى).
Musa(موسى); his point is not to win; His point is to give Da'wah(دعوة).
So he wanted to give them another chance.
So Musa(موسى) told them;
قَالَ لَهُم مُّوسَىٰ وَيْلَكُمْ لَا تَفْتَرُواْ عَلَى ٱللَّهِ كَذِبًا فَيُسْحِتَكُم بِعَذَابٍۢ ۖ
وَقَدْ خَابَ مَنِ ٱفْتَرَىٰ۝
Moses said to them; Woe unto you invent not a lie against Allah, lest He should destroy you completely by a torment.
And surely he who invents a lie against Allah will fail miserably.
He's giving them another chance.
He's saying; this is a lie against the Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
And if you continue with that; you will end up failing.
These words were discussed by the magicians.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَتَنَٰزَعُوٓاْ أَمْرَهُم بَيْنَهُمْ وَأَسَرُّواْ ٱلنَّجْوَىٰ۝
Allah says; then they debated with one another; what they must do and they kept their talk secret.
They were discussing; is this man really a prophet or is he a magician?
In the end, they settled the argument and said he's a magician.
And this is our plan and this is what we're going to do.
And Firaun(فرعون) said and they said with him;
قَالُوٓاْ إِنْ هَٰذَٰنِ لَسَٰحِرَٰنِ يُرِيدَانِ أَن يُخْرِجَاكُم مِّنْ أَرْضِكُم بِسِحْرِهِمَا وَيَذْهَبَا بِطَرِيقَتِكُمُ ٱلْمُثْلَىٰ۝
These are two magicians; Their object is to drive you out of your land with their magic and overcome your chiefs and nobles.
فَأَجْمِعُواْ كَيْدَكُمْ ثُمَّ ٱئْتُواْ صَفًّا ۚ
وَقَدْ أَفْلَحَ ٱلْيَوْمَ مَنِ ٱسْتَعْلَىٰ۝
So, devise your plot and then assemble in a line and whoever overcomes this day, will be indeed successful.
He told them; assemble in a line.
So imagine with me; this is a festival.
All of the people of Egypt are there; surrounding this battlefield.
And one side of the battlefield; 70 magicians lined up with all of their equipment.
And on the other side; Musa(موسى) standing alone and his brother behind him.
Imagine the scene; 70 magicians; that is the minimum number,
imagine it's 15,000, in ranks; lines with all of their equipment; with all of their tools.
And Musa(موسى) is standing alone on the other side; And all of the people of Egypt are surrounding them and watching.
And they devise their plan.
So, they said;
قَالُواْ يَٰمُوسَىٰٓ إِمَّآ أَن تُلْقِىَ وَإِمَّآ أَن نَّكُونَ أَوَّلَ مَنْ أَلْقَىٰ۝
Oh Musa(موسى)! Either you throw your stick first or we will be the first to throw.
قَالَ بَلْ أَلْقُواْ ۖ
He said; throw your sticks.
So they threw their sticks and their ropes.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَإِذَا حِبَالُهُمْ وَعِصِيُّهُمْ يُخَيَّلُ إِلَيْهِ مِن سِحْرِهِمْ أَنَّهَا تَسْعَىٰ۝
Then behold their ropes and their sticks by their magic, appeared to him as though they moved fast.
And these were not amateur magicians or weak in their field.
These were strong professional and they were the best, maybe the world has ever seen in magic.
Because Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says in the other Ayah(آية);
قَالَ أَلْقُواْ ۖ فَلَمَّآ أَلْقَوْاْ سَحَرُوٓاْ أَعْيُنَ ٱلنَّاسِ وَٱسْتَرْهَبُوهُمْ وَجَآءُو بِسِحْرٍ عَظِيمٍۢ۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says; When they threw their sticks and their ropes; they have made magic and illusion on the eyes of people.
وَٱسْتَرْهَبُوهُمْ
They put fear in the hearts of people.
وَجَآءُو بِسِحْرٍ عَظِيمٍۢ۝
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is saying; This is great magic.
Imagine; how powerful it would have been.
First of all;
سَحَرُوٓاْ أَعْيُنَ ٱلنَّاسِ
أَعْيُنَ ٱلنَّاسِ
The magic was on the eyes of men; meaning that, These sticks and ropes weren't really snakes.
Because we cannot give life to the dead.
Therefore, it was an illusion; an optical illusion.
That is, what it is.
Because, we do not control the difference between life and death and that is; Ar-Rooh(الروح).
ٱلرُّوحُ مِنْ أَمْرِ رَبِّى
يَسْـَٔلُونَكَ عَنِ ٱلرُّوحِ ۖ
They ask you about the soul.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى is telling Muhammadﷺ;
قُلِ ٱلرُّوحُ مِنْ أَمْرِ رَبِّى وَمَآ أُوتِيتُم مِّنَ ٱلْعِلْمِ إِلَّا قَلِيلًا۝
Tell them that, the soul; the knowledge of the soul belongs to Allah and you only have little knowledge.
This is something that only Allahسُبحانه وتعالى controls.
So this magic was an illusion.
But Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
وَٱسْتَرْهَبُوهُمْ
When  the people saw this, they were afraid and terrified.
So imagine; the people of Egypt surrounding this stadium or this battlefield
and all of them were afraid and terrified when they saw; what the magician's have done?
What do you think the response of Musa(موسى) would be?
And he is with them in the field.
Remember; what happened before with Musa(موسى) when his stick started moving?
What happened?
فَوَلَّىٰ مُدْبِرًا وَلَمْ يُعَقِّبْ ۚ
He ran away and he did not look back.
And it was one stick.
But now, look at the response of Musa(موسى);  seventy magicians or 15,000; throwing their sticks and their ropes;
All the people around them are terrified.
Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says;
فَأَوْجَسَ فِى نَفْسِهِۦ خِيفَةً مُّوسَىٰ۝
Musa(موسى) conceived fear.
Where?
In his heart.
But it did not show on his reaction; It did not show on his action; It did not show at all on Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى).
It remained the natural human response in the heart.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى then said;
قُلْنَا لَا تَخَفْ إِنَّكَ أَنتَ ٱلْأَعْلَىٰ۝
Fear not, surely you will have the upper hand.
Before he had fear in his heart and he acted upon it; He ran away and he didn't look back.
Now, it was a natural human fear in the heart.
But it's not affected Syedina Musa(سيدنا موسى) and that is what Eeman(ايمان) does.
You still go through the natural human reactions or feelings of fear and doubt, all of these things that come to the heart,
but the believer is able to suppress them and is able to eliminate them.
And that is the difference between the believer and the non believer.
So, Musa(موسى) here; he only concieved the little bit of fear in his heart but it did not affect him whatsoever.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى then gave Musa(موسى) Itma'nan(اطمئينان); he gave him tranquility.
So that, small fear in the heart was eliminated and taken out of his heart.
وَأَلْقِ مَا فِى يَمِينِكَ
And throw that, which is in your right hand.
Now; the 70 magicians have their sticks and their ropes shaking and moving.
And then Allahسُبحانه وتعالى tells Musa(موسى) throw; what is in your right hand.
تَلْقَفْ مَا صَنَعُوٓاْ ۖ
It will eat up everything that they made.
إِنَّمَا صَنَعُواْ كَيْدُ سَٰحِرٍۢ ۖ وَلَا يُفْلِحُ ٱلسَّاحِرُ حَيْثُ أَتَىٰ۝
This is a plot of a magician and the plots of the magicians are not successful wherever they are.
What is the difference between the stick of Musa(موسى) and the sticks of the magicians?
The difference is that, the stick of Musa(موسى) had a living soul in it, that transformed the stick into a real snake.
So it ate up all of their ropes.
What was the response of the magicians?
Who are the ones among all of these people, who are watching, who are the experts?
Who are the ones who understand what's going on?
The Magicians.
Firaun(فرعون) is stubborn.
He knows the truth.
وَٱسْتَيْقَنَتْهَآ أَنفُسُهُمْ
He knew the truth, but he doesn't want to believe.
The people of Egypt surrounding are followers of Firaun(فرعون).
Whatever Firaun(فرعون) says; we're going to follow him.
فَٱسْتَخَفَّ قَوْمَهُۥ فَأَطَاعُوهُ ۚ
He belittled his people, so they followed him.
But the ones; who have understanding of the reality of the situation of the magicians;
So, when they saw this; they understood that, this is not magic.
We are the experts in magic.
We know magic from A to Z.
We know everything about it; This is not magic.
This is not magic; this is a miracle from Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
So, when they saw that, the reaction was;
فَأُلْقِىَ ٱلسَّحَرَةُ سُجَّدًا
They made Sujood(سجود) to Allahسُبحانه وتعالى and said;
قَالُوٓاْ ءَامَنَّا بِرَبِّ هَٰرُونَ وَمُوسَىٰ
We believed in the Lord of Haroon(هارون) and Musa(موسى).
Firaun(فرعون) said;
قَالَ ءَامَنتُمْ لَهُۥ قَبْلَ أَنْ ءَاذَنَ لَكُمْ ۖ
He said;
You believed in him before I gave you permission.
Look at, how much control Firaun(فرعون) had over people.
He even wants them to take permission from him, when they want to become Muslim.
You have to get permission; a permit to believe in Musa(موسى).
That is, how much control Firaun(فرعون) had, over the lives of people.
قَالَ ءَامَنتُمْ لَهُۥ قَبْلَ أَنْ ءَاذَنَ لَكُمْ ۖ إِنَّهُۥ لَكَبِيرُكُمُ ٱلَّذِى عَلَّمَكُمُ ٱلسِّحْرَ
Firaun(فرعون) said; He is your teacher; Musa(موسى) is your teacher, who taught you magic.
And then he threatened them and said;
فَلَأُقَطِّعَنَّ أَيْدِيَكُمْ وَأَرْجُلَكُم مِّنْ خِلَٰفٍۢ وَلَأُصَلِّبَنَّكُمْ فِى جُذُوعِ ٱلنَّخْلِ
وَلَأُصَلِّبَنَّكُمْ فِى جُذُوعِ ٱلنَّخْلِ وَلَتَعْلَمُنَّ أَيُّنَآ أَشَدُّ عَذَابًا وَأَبْقَىٰ۝
Verily, he is your chief, who taught to you magic.
So, I will surely cut off your hands and your feet on opposite sides and I will surely crucify you on the trunks of palm trees.
And then notice, what Firaun(فرعون) said;
قَالَ فِرْعَوْنُ ءَامَنتُم بِهِۦ قَبْلَ أَنْ ءَاذَنَ لَكُمْ ۖ إِنَّ هَٰذَا لَمَكْرٌ مَّكَرْتُمُوهُ فِى ٱلْمَدِينَةِ لِتُخْرِجُواْ مِنْهَآ أَهْلَهَا ۖ فَسَوْفَ تَعْلَمُونَ۝
Firaun(فرعون) said; This is a conspiracy between you and Musa(موسى), which you have agreed about in the town before you came here;
Look at this a blunt lie.
He said; this is a conspiracy.
You were conspiring with Musa(موسى) before you came here.
In Surat-u-Shu'ara(سورةالشعراء); Allahسُبحانه وتعالى says that, when the magicians came and had their first meeting with Firaun(فرعون).
The magicians were gathered from all over Egypt.
When they were brought to Egypt and they had their first meeting with Firaun(فرعون), what did they say?
What is the first thing the magician's told Firaun(فرعون), when they met with him?
In the first meeting with Firaun(فرعون), they said;
اَئِنَّ لَنَا لَأَجْرًا إِن كُنَّا نَحْنُ ٱلْغَٰلِبِينَ۝
Are you going to reward us, if we win?
So, they were in it for the money.
That is why, they came; they want the reward.
What did Firaun(فرعون) say?
Yes, and you will also be close to me.
So Firaun(فرعون), not only is going to give them wealth but he's going to give them power and position.
They came for small worldly gain.
And when they went into the field,
it is said; Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) says that, these magicians stood up and they threw their sticks and their ropes and they were chanting;
بِعِزَّةِ فِرْعَوْنَ إِنَّا لَنَحْنُ ٱلْغَٰلِبُونَ۝
In the name of Firaun(فرعون); We are going to win.
In the name of Firaun(فرعون); We're going to win.
And they were chanting these words.
These magicians now became believers.
And Firaun(فرعون) told them; I will kill you and I will crucify you.
He will kill them in a cruel way.
He's going to chop out; their arms and their legs and he's going to crucify them on palm trees.
What was the response of the magicians now?
قَالُواْ لَن نُّؤْثِرَكَ عَلَىٰ مَا جَآءَنَا مِنَ ٱلْبَيِّنَٰتِ وَٱلَّذِى فَطَرَنَا ۖ
فَٱقْضِ مَآ أَنتَ قَاضٍ ۖ إِنَّمَا تَقْضِى هَٰذِهِ ٱلْحَيَوٰةَ ٱلدُّنْيَآ۝
They said; We prefer you not over the clear signs that have came to us and to him, Allah who created us.
So decree whatever you desire to decree, for you can only decree regarding the life of this world.
إِنَّآ ءَامَنَّا بِرَبِّنَا لِيَغْفِرَ لَنَا خَطَٰيَٰنَا وَمَآ أَكْرَهْتَنَا عَلَيْهِ مِنَ ٱلسِّحْرِ ۗ وَٱللَّهُ خَيْرٌ وَأَبْقَىٰٓ۝
Verily, we have believed in our Lord that He may forgive us our faults and the magic to which you have compelled us to do.
And Allah is better as regards reward in comparison to yours.
The reward of Allah is better than yours.
Look at, what Eeman(ايمان) does.
The same people who came and were asking for money, are now saying;
We are not only willing to give our wealth; We're willing to give our life for the sake of Allah because the reward of a Allah is better.
That is what Eeman(ايمان) does.
And if our Eeman(ايمان) is not carrying us to that level than that means, our Eeman(ايمان) is very weak.
Because  with the magicians; their Eeman(ايمان) transformed them from people who came to beg from Firaun(فرعون);
to people who are willing to give their lives in the sake of Allahسُبحانه وتعالى.
That is Eeman(ايمان).
If our Eeman(ايمان) is not transforming us in that way, then we have a problem with our Eeman(ايمان).
If we're not willing to give in the sake of Allah and to provide and to sacrifice, what Eeman(ايمان) do we have?
Because the Deen(دِيْن) is;
تضحية
It's to sacrifice.
And they died on Eeman(ايمان) and they were Shuhadaa(شُهَدآء).
They died in the sake of Allah.
These magicians, who were committing one of the major crimes and sins; magic, Eeman(ايمان) transformed them.
And Allahسُبحانه وتعالى accepts the Tawbah(توبة) of anyone and then they became Shuhadaa(شُهَدآء) in the end.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْتسليما كثيرا